Good evening. Good evening and welcome.
I call to order this meeting of council
for Tuesday, March 25th, 2025. Uh one
point of order. Uh administration bill
number 22025 which is listed on the
agenda later this evening for its first
reading uh would not be presented today.
Um, and for all those able and willing,
please stand for the pledge of
allegiance to the flag of the United
States of America and to the stands
nationy for all.
Mr. Harris, Mr. Harris, can you please
call the role of members? Yes, Mr. Vice
Press. Mr. man here, Mr. Royo here, Mr.
Gleas here, Miss Craig here, Miss Diaz
here, Mr. Hirs here, and President B.
Council President B is excuses excused
this evening. A few friendly reminders.
Please note, please note this meeting is
being livereamed and recorded. If you
are making a public comment this
evening, please do so at the microphone
and state your name and address for the
meeting record. Also, please be sure to
silence any cell phones and
devices. First, I'll hear a motion for
the approval of the March 11th, 2025
meeting minutes. Motion to approve.
Second. Have a motion in a second. Mr.
Harris,
Mr. Madden, I. Mr. Roya, I. Mr. Gleas,
I. Miss Greg, I. Miss Diaz. I. Mr.
Harsh. I.
Next, we'll hear any proclamations,
honors, awards, and resolutions of
recognition. Mr. Harris, do we have any?
We do. The first is
uh council resolution number
212025. A resolution of the council of
the city of Lancaster designating March
2025 as women's history month in the
city of Lancaster, Pennsylvania.
Motion to approve. Second. Second. We
have a motion and a second. Uh this
resolution was brought forward by
Council President BK honoring Women's
History Month. Um any I'll open it up
for any council comments.
Any comments from the public?
Mr. Harris. Mr. Man. I. Mr. Roya. I. Mr.
Gleas. I. Miss. Craig. I. Miss. Diaz. I.
Mr. Harsh. I.
We'll move into our first public comment
period. Uh this is reserved for citizens
who have contacted the city clerk prior
to the meeting to request opportunity to
address city council. The duration of
comments are limited to three minutes.
Uh Mr. Harris, do we have any? Yes, we
do. Uh first this evening is Amed
Zaki and please make sure the green
light is on microphone.
There you go.
Hello. Good evening, city council member
and Miss Mayor. My name is Ahmed Zaki,
336 Bever Street, Lancaster,
PA.
Uh, a lot of people know our story. I
think we no need to repeat it again. I'm
here again for the third time to talk
about
justice unfortunately that there is no
justice. Uh we post uh on our Facebook
page about our problems.
Some people uh recommend us to go to
city council and others you are problem
city
council and we got some uh feedback or
some help from this to member of the
city council personal help.
Unfortunately, it was not useful and uh
we we expected from city council as the
people recommend us that maybe they
could help
us give recommend us to the court or
help us with their public defender or
fortunately nobody was scared about
this even 50% of our problem caused by
city Lancaster city inspection
department but uh nobody was cared
And we all we all and at the end of the
things everybody I think b to the flag
and the h of the the song was
justice that always pay take me my
attention justice when I'm hearing the
justice and I think I I find I got
allergic to the name of the justice
because there's no
justice I I I'm as a citizen when I
swore to say to this country I followed
the law. I paid everything. I never did
anything wrong. But official nobody
followed the
law. I think by barking or crying
nothing will change. It is already
written in modern
slavery book. There is no justice for
the poor
people. If there is something of
everything is a scam, a circle kind of a
scam in the court that turning you
around again. continue coming back to
the
money. I should teach my kids and
everybody should
teach that they be they should be
careful. How system working
here and who the right who is right who
is wrong is not a problem. Who is the
richer who have money? They are the
winner. And we cannot make American
great again. Some people saying again or
right now any time without
justice justice is the greatest
greatness for everything with the
without justice a country cannot be
country a father cannot be a father a
society cannot be a society if there is
no justice that's all I think I have to
get keep silent
and and sit in my
place and I think I cannot do anything
more of this I I what what I did I did
for three times
near after this I have to keep my
problem in my heart and sit with myself.
Thank you so
much for justice.
Our next speaker is Mora.
Hi, my name is Mora Condan Umul and I
live at 231 North Shippen Street. Thank
you all for giving me a few
minutes. 6 and a half years ago, I lost
my son to firearm
suicide. And over the last couple of
years, to try to deal with my grief and
loss, I decided to get involved with U.
Mom's Demand Action for Gun Sense and
Ceasefire
Pennsylvania. I learned there I learned
with these organizations that most gun
deaths in this country are
suicides. That shocked me. Most gun
deaths in this country are suicides. I
assume that might be shocking to a lot
of people.
Ceasefire Pennsylvania and Moms Demand
Action are dedicated to reducing or
hopefully eliminating gun violence of
all kinds, including suicide.
So, I'm here tonight to encourage all
members of city council and all city
leaders and anybody else who's
interested that's here tonight to attend
a Ceasefire
Pennsylvania panel discussion on this
Thursday night at 6:30. It's be it's
being hosted by Benchmark program, which
perhaps you're familiar with that
wonderful program, a very
impactful community violence
intervention program on South Prince
Street. We'd be so grateful. I would be
so grateful for as many of you as
possible. Some of you have actually
already RSVPd and I'm so grateful for
that. I'd be so delighted. We'd all be
so delighted to see as many of you and
the mayor as well if uh if you are
available. And as I said, it's open to
anybody who's interested. I have a QR
code with the registration information
about the details and um RSVP
information
here. Thank
you. Next speaker is Daryl Gase.
Hi, my name is Daryl Legacy. I live in
the 100 block of North
Mary. Uh, thank you so much for letting
me speak here tonight. I was going to
come and speak about the use of force
incident from uh almost a month ago now.
Um, but I think other people are going
to do a better job of that. So, instead
I'm going to talk about the council and
the future of the council. So, there's
very likely that next year there's
potentially a vacancy on the city
council, right? If one of the two city
councilors who are running for mayor
win, um there'll be a vacancy. The last
time there was a vacancy, you all asked
for applicants and you chose somebody.
And so, I hope you do that again if
there ends up being a vacancy. And if
you do, I'm gonna apply. But here's the
thing. I hope you don't pick me. I live
in the southern end of Chestnut Hill,
right? Not the rich fancy area, but
still Chestnut Hill. If I uh go out my
front door and lean a little bit, I can
actually see the mayor's house or at
least your front door. Uh my area
doesn't need more money or more
investment, right? There are lots of
parts of this city that need it. So
instead, I hope you pick somebody who's
workingass. I hope you pick somebody who
makes under, say, $50,000 a year. I hope
you pick somebody who's paycheck to
paycheck in the Southwest or maybe in
the Southeast. I hope you pick a parent.
And here's the radical part. Pick a
renter. There's no reason you cannot,
according to the regulations, pick
someone who rents in the city. I think
that would make a huge difference. So,
here's the other thing. I know that the
council has certain powers and certain
things they can't do. You can't fire the
police chief. You can't suspend the
officers. You can't demand that officers
walk a beat. But what you can do, and I
hope you will, is you can call out the
chief when he's wrong. And you can call
out the mayor when I think the mayor is
wrong. You can do it here at city
council. You make proclamations. You can
do it personally. You can do it in the
newspaper. You can go to protests. You
can lead protests. You can march with
us. And I think we need to see more of
that. It's not going to help your
political advancement. Like, if you do
that, you're probably not going to
become mayor or state representative or
state senator. But here's the thing.
It's the right thing to
do. You have a chance here to change
things, right? And I think and hope that
you're spending, let's say, one term
changing things here. and then you go
back and go to your old job instead of
staying on the council for terms and
terms and terms and not changing things.
This is your chance to change the lives
of people that live in this city. And
there's a lot of things that I think you
can do and I think one of them is
standing up and being more vocal. So I
hope you do.
Mr. Harrison, next speaker. Next speaker
is John Maya.
Good evening everyone. I'm John Minina
of 24 West Main Street, Strasburg,
Pennsylvania. I'm sick and tired of
being sick and tired. That's what Fanny
Liu Hamer said to the world in 1964.
And tonight, during Women's History
Month, we honor her legacy by telling
the truth. We too are sick and tired.
Sick and tired of the same cycle. A
video goes viral. Community members
express outrage and the police respond
with a statement that tells us nothing
except that once again, the public is
wrong and the department is
right. But this time, Lancaster showed
up two weeks ago. residents, partners,
and yes, members of this very council
agreed that what happened on March 2nd
is not what community policing should
look like. And yet, we've been here
before. This being the third incident as
many months where force was used instead
of deescalation, instead of
transparency, we get a press conference
that blamed the kids, that blamed the
parents and the community,
all while protecting the system that
failed it.
We don't need more excuses. We need
action. And that is why we submitted our
resolution two weeks ago. We asked for
an independent review of the March 2nd
incident, not one led by the department
itself.
The department can't police itself.
That's why we demanded it.
Public release of all past and future
use of force reports. We want to track
patterns and hold systems
accountable. Clarity around the role and
authority of the public safety
committee. And last, but certainly not
least, establishing a civilian review
board so the people have a seat at the
table where their safety is being
decided. Let's be clear, this is not
just about one incident or one officer.
This is about trust. Trust that has been
broken. But it can be rebuilt if courage
is shown now.
Courage means facing the hard truths
about our systems. It means not
retreating in the bureaucracy or hiding
behind internal reviews. It means
standing up and saying we will not
accept this as normal. We are not here
to attack you. We are here because we
believe Lancaster can do better and we
know you believe that too. But belief
without action is
complicity. So tonight we ask for more
than words. We ask for partnership,
policy, and political will to stand with
the people who elected you. As Dr.
Martin Luther as do, excuse me, as Dr.
Martin Luther King Jr. once said, "There
comes a time when one must take a
position that is neither safe nor
politic nor popular, but he must take it
because his conscience tells him it is
right." That time is now. Thank you.
Next speaker is Abby Haney.
Hi, thank you. My name is Abby Haney. I
live on the 600 block of East Madison
Street and today I come to you as
co-chair of the Lancaster Democratic
Socialist of America. The press
conference held by Chief Mendes and
Mayor Srachi on March 18th was nothing
more than an attempt to deflect blame
from the police department onto
literally anyone else, the kids in the
city, their families, and the community.
It was also a tacid endorsement of the
treatment of these children and what
they received, regardless of prior
interactions that they had with the
police. There was no excuse for the
force that was used on them. This was
and will continue to be a failure of the
Lancaster Police Department to
deescalate.
Frankly, it was disgusting that these
kids were characterized as criminals and
that the insinuation for the use of
force was that they could have been
carrying guns. The issue of juvenile gun
control in Lancaster had absolutely
nothing to do with the situation. It was
yet another instance of deflecting blame
onto anyone but the officers involved.
The statement spoke of the ways your
department is involved in the Lancaster
community. Sure, it's great that one of
your officers plays basketball once a
week with kids, but that doesn't build
trust. what officers can be hired from
outside of Lancaster City to come into
our community to police black and brown
people there. It's automatically an
imbalance of power and it seems clear to
us why there's a lack of trust and
respect and to escape the commu and to
scapegoat the community to accuse them
of not showing up for their kids is
disingenuous. Lancaster is home to
diverse community organizations that
serve our youth. finally to give
yourselves a pat on the back about your
accreditation and in your statement with
a call for folks to join the police
department if they want to stay in
public safety was tonedeaf and out of
touch instead of using more taxpayer
dollars on expanding policing. Why
doesn't the city establish a public
safety commission or civilian review
board where members of this community
have the agency to hold our police
department accountable? Surely a good
faith demonstration of trust would
include community oversight. Our demands
as a collective of organizations remain
resolute. Number one, an update on the
status of an independent review process.
We cannot trust the police to
investigate themselves impartially.
Number two, a public commitment to
making all past and future use of force
reports available to residents, not just
quarterly. And three, to establish a
public safety commission or have a plan
in place for a civilian review board.
These demands are not radical. They are
a step towards the transparency and
accountability that members of this very
council called for at the last city
council meeting. Should they be
unwilling to compromise, it sends a
message that the city and its governing
bodies are unwilling to prioritize
resident safety. Lancaster DSA is
calling on you to have the moral courage
and fortitude to follow through on these
demands. We refuse to have our children
placed this way. Thank you,
Mr. Harris. Next speaker. Next speaker
is Jackie
Snider. And next speaker is Megan
Keller. And the next is Cy Gomez.
[Music]
Susie Gomez, 100 block of North
Reservoir Street.
going to hand you guys a document.
Okay. So you have in front of you
um a page from the newspaper article
where Amanda, Izzy, and Xavier and Jamie
was also in a riot at the
protest here. Uh it was told to this
council that they were to create um a
commission for blacks and browns
affairs. Can you since Amanda's not
here, Jamie, tell me what happened to
that 2020 policy that you guys had
pushed.
Are you done with your public comment?
I'm sorry. Are you done with your public
comment?
Am I done with my public comment? That's
a question, sir. Yes. Are you refusing
to answer? Are you done with your public
comment, Miss Goldman? No, I'm not done
with my public comment. I'm asking a
question.
Are you refusing to answer? There was a
policy that was pushed in 2020 and Miss
Bake had asked council to do the same
exact thing. And what you see in front
of you is a draft that Lancaster can
adapt um or adopt since nothing happened
in 2020. Here's a draft that Janet gave
me from Harrisburg City Council.
But we all know that nothing will happen
because you block her on everything and
you can't even answer a question. Now,
when you were involved in this protest,
you guys fought to put in place a
commission board to hold these officers
accountable. What I'm asking you is a
simple question. What happened? It was
show. Are you done with your public
comment, Miss Goldz? That's what
happened. Yeah.
I think I'm done with my public comment
because it goes to show that you don't
even have an answer. It goes to show
that you know you're in question also.
Thank you, Miss Gomez. And from my
understanding, there was a commission
that was uh established at the time. Uh
there was also a police working group
that was established uh during uh those
protests. Mr. Harris, any other
speakers?
Next speaker is Jontel Tolen.
Good evening. Uh John telling first and
only block of wise
a I'm not sure if the Lancaster City
Police Department is aware of this, but
the excuses they have given, claiming
videos show only part of the story,
labeling these children as uh juveniles
to criminalize them and attempting to
shift the narrative are not having the
effect they think they should. These are
children and I do not care what they
have done. Their treatment at the hands
of police was unjustifiable. I am
certain if this had happened in lit or
even here within city borders and our
current department. If these were
average white children from litis, the
response would have been vastly
different. That is the point. The
excessive force used especially on
minors was not justified. In an era
where state sanctioned violence and
suppression are becoming alarmingly
alarmingly normalized, the swift
response from the community is more than
warranted. It is our right to challenge
the rights of your own constituents. To
demand that we accept violence against
our children without push back speaks
volumes about who you are and what you
truly represent. You must ask yourselves
which side of history do you stand on.
The press conference held by Chief
Mendes and Mayor Sarra was not an
attempt at accountability. It was a
deflection, distraction, and an insult
to the people de uh demanding real
answers. Instead of transparency, they
chose to place blame on the children,
their families, and the broader Langster
community, completely ignoring the fact
that it was the police who escalated
this situation. They justified the
unjustifiable. Blaming the people you
are supposed to serve does not erase the
failure of your leadership. The refusal,
the refusal to release the body camera
footage, the dismissal of public
concern, and the unwillingness to engage
with the actual demands of this
community prove that the administration
does not value the voices of those
seeking justice. Instead working to
build trust, you offer bare minimum lip
service. Instead of listening to the
people, you retreat into the empty
statements and excuses. But let me make
something clear. This community is not
letting up. We are not going anywhere.
If there is no trust, there will be
constant calls for accountability. If
there is no justice, there will be a
constant chorus of voices demanding
change. If there is no action, there
will be continued pressure,
confrontation, and resistance. At every
turn, we will not be pacified. We will
not be silenced. Let me be absolutely
clear about what is happening here. This
is not just about one incident. This is
about a long pattern of abuse, a long
pattern of black and brown residents
being brutalized, a long pattern of
police being given free reign to harm
without consequence. This is about
accountability, not just for what
happened on March 2nd, but for the
policing practices that have allowed to
keep happening. So, let me make this
even clearer. We will not stop until
justice is served. We will not stop
until these demands are met. We will not
stop until real systemic change is made.
If you think we will forget, if you
think we will grow tired and move on,
you are mistaken. The people of
Lancaster are watching. The history is
recording how you choose to respond.
This moment is defining. The question
is, will you act with integrity or
accountability? Or will you allow the
city's leadership to be defined by
deflection, distraction, and dishonesty?
And why that is why Lincoln
organizations alongside this community
are making demands. The city has a
choice. Either meet these demands or be
prepared for the relentless, unwavering
push back. We are not here to ask
politely. We are not here to wait until
the outrage dies down and officials in
power hope we forget. We are here to
demand real structural change. And
here's what that looks like. An
independent review of the incident
completely outside of Lincoln City
Police Department. Their word alone is
not enough. Their internal review
already cleared the officers involved.
We do not trust a system that
investigates itself. What do you take us
for? Public access to past and present
use of force records uh reports.
Transparency is not optional. If you
have nothing to hide, then release the
records. Let the community see the
truth. A civilian review board with
actual power. Why is there no permanent
independent oversight of policing? A
public safety commission is not a
radical idea. It is a necessity.
Immediate action against our officer
Heatfield and the other officers
involved. We call for death duty within
48 hours. We call for the changes
against these youth to be dropped. And
yet no action has been taken. That is
unacceptable. Let me be clear. This does
not end here. They can hold press
conferences. They can spin their
narratives. They can pretend they are
doing their jobs. But as long as they
refuse to be accountable, the city will
be filled with voices demanding change.
You do not get to use excessive force
and expect the people to be silent. You
do not get to betray your constituents
and then act surprised when we push
back. History is watching. Lancaster
will be remembered for what it choose to
do at this moment. And we will make damn
sure they know the people are not
backing down. We are not asking for We
are asking for change. We are We are not
asking for change. We are demanding it.
And we will not stop until we see it
happen. Thank you.
Mr. Harris,
that was the last the first public
comment period. Thank you, Mr. Harris.
Uh, I'll close out the initial public
comment period. As a reminder, there
will be one at the conclusion of this
meeting or the uh end of the legislative
agenda. Uh, next is reports requested by
council. Mr. Harris, we have none
tonight. Thank you. Uh, next we have
interim reports of committees of
council. We have none of those either.
Thank you, Mr. Harris. Uh, we'll move
into our legislative agenda. Uh, first
we'll begin with the ordinance of excuse
me, administration bill number 1225.
an ordinance authorizing the incurrence
of non-electoral debt of the city of
Lancaster, Lancaster County,
Pennsylvania by issuance of 41,900
uh sorry
41,95,000 of principal amount general
obligation bonds series of 2025 issued
for the purpose of providing funds for
launch general municipal projects
including upgrades and improvements to
the city's wastewater collection and
treatment facilities.
the city's water treatment and
distribution facilities, the city's
parks and related facilities, the
streets and traffic signals within the
city and related facilities, each as set
forth in exhibit Attached year two and
other capital projects of the city as
determined by the city. Two,
capitalizing interest on the bonds and
three paying the cost of issuing and
ensuring the bonds determined to sell
the series of 2025 bonds. the 2025 bonds
at a private sale by invitation
approving the form of the series of 2025
bonds. Fixing the number, date,
interest, and maturities in the 2025
bonds. Making a covenant for the payment
of the debt service on the 2025 bonds.
Pledging the full faith, credit, and
taxing power of this city in support of
such bonds. providing for the filing of
required documents, providing for the
appointment of a sink syncing fund
depository for the 2025 bonds, and
authorizing execution, sale, and
delivery thereof, and other necessary
action.
Motion to
approve. Second,
uh, Mr. Harris, I would also like to
make a motion to amend the bill.
Can you turn up the volume? It's very
hard to hear. We cannot hear. Sorry, the
mic is in. The volume's low. It's hard
to hear. And I'm sorry. This a motion to
amend. Motion to amend the bill. We need
a second for that.
Sec. And Mr. Harris, please forgive me.
Uh should I go ahead and read the motion
to amend at this time? Yes. Yes. Thank
you.
Uh the motion for the amend or the
motion to amend uh bond council has
provided each of us with a blackline
version of the ordinance authorizing the
directing the issuance of the general
obligation bonds series of 2025 in an
original principal amount equal to 41
million95 4195,000.
Such ordinance was introduced as
administrative bill number 1 2025 before
this council on March 11th, 2025. I
hereby move to amend the ordinance
labeled administration bill number one
2025 to include the additions,
deletions, and other changes changes
referenced on such blank black lined
version of the ordinance which will be
rewarded with the minutes of this
meeting and which can be summarized as
follows. In the third line of the
caption, deleting dollar sign blank and
replacing it with
$41,95,000. In the third whereas
clauses, deleting dollar sign blank and
replacing it with
$41,95,000. Inserting into the fifth
whereas clause the name Robert Wbard and
Company Incorporated as the purchaser.
in the six whereas clauses, deleting
dollar sign blank and replacing it with
41,863,16. In section one of the
ordinance, deleting dollar sign blank
and replacing it with
$41,95,000 as the amount of indebtedness
authorized by the ordinance. In section
two of the ordinance, deleting dollar
sign blank and replacing it with
$41,95,000 as the aggregate principal
amount of general obligation bonds
series of 2025 authorized by the
ordinance. In section nine of the
ordinance, inserting the optional
redemption provisions of the bonds as
the bonds which are stated to mature on
or after November 1, 2025 are subject to
redemption prior to maturity at the
option of the city in hope or in part on
November 1, 2034 or any date thereafter.
on exhibit C attaching the amortization
schedule as provided by the purchaser. A
copy of the proposal of the purchaser
has been attached to the ordinance as
exhibit ex as exhibit
D. That is the
motion.
Second, we have a motion and a second
and I will invite Director Campbell to
uh give us a explanation on uh plane
levels.
Thank you. Um so this is the second
reading for the ordinance for the 2025
general obligation bond. Um Daryl is
handing out some information that he
will discuss in just a minute. Um but as
you've heard from the uh lengthy motion.
Uh the amounts have been finalized based
on the bond auction which happened today
and the and the final costs. Um we
discussed the project list and amounts
um in detail at the finance committee on
March 3rd. Um, so we won't get into that
tonight. Um, but before Daryl comes to
talk about the um the final numbers, I
did want to just uh share a note on our
bond rating. Um, with so with each
proposed bond financing, Moody's um is
our bond rider and they do an extensive
review of our financial information to
to determine if an update of our bond
rating is warranted. last summer. Um, so
in 2024, Moody's moved us from an A3
rating with a negative outlook to an A3
rating with a stable outlook. And in
review for this current bond financing,
um, at the beginning of March, Moody's
has moved this to an A3 rating with a
positive outlook, which is great news.
Um, they saw the adoption of home rules,
a very positive move for the city. um as
well as small increases in recent years
to our emergency fund balances. Um this
rating plays a key role in many things
um but in including directly affecting
the interest rate for the bonds um that
we receive on B bond financing. So I did
want to just note that. And on that
note, I'm going to ask Darl to come and
talk about the numbers.
Thank you, Miss Campbell. Uh good
evening members, mayor and members of
council. Um with with that introduction,
um I'm just really going to update you
on discussion we had during the finance
committee on uh March the 3rd. Uh Miss
Campbell already indicated that uh we
went through the rating process. Uh we
also put together an official statement
or preliminary official statement. It's
a lot of information kind of good
background on the city uh economic
demographic uh financial information
that's been provided uh to Mr. Harris
and I believe it's been been provided to
you as well electronically. So you know
if if you're looking for something to
review certainly some good information
about the city. This is really what's
used to essentially market the bonds. So
uh we wanted to get that to you for your
review. Um, uh, Tina shared the great
news, uh, that the, uh, city's bond
rating was affirmed at A3 and that you
were given a positive outlook. Sounds
just like it sounds. Positive outlook,
meaning the city has a positive outlook
from a financial perspective. Um, so
since uh we we met on at the finance
committee, uh, again, we've been working
through that process to bring these
bonds to market. uh you had your first
reading on March 11th and today as I
think you're aware we have a bond
auction uh to basically bid out your
bonds uh to really all underwriters uh
really from coast to coast to really bid
it out and know that we're getting you
the best rates available in the market
today. Um so we did that today uh from
12 to 12:15. Uh in this handout uh on
page one is the summary. Um, we
ultimately got uh two biders to bid on
your bonds. They submitted four bids
throughout those 15 minutes. Um, it's
important to talk even though we have
two biders. Uh, some of these biders,
particularly Robert Baird, uh, works
with a number of firms. There's actually
25 firms in their so-called syndicate.
So, you're really, even though you see
it, okay, it's two biders, it's really
more biders who are actually actually
engaged in uh, purchasing your bonds.
you know, you go through this
competitive process to again get you the
best rate available. Um, at the end of
the day, uh, Robert Baird, uh, the
highlighted, came in at the best
interest rate of 4.742, a lot more
decimal points. Um, uh, the other bidder
was Wells Fargo. Uh, the their best next
bid was
4.85%. They actually improved their bid
throughout the process by 008%. To put
those numbers in perspective, the
difference between the
4.74% and the
4.85% is about
$880,000 in interest expense. So
actually looking at the best bid and the
first, if you call it worst bid, you
know, that was about 2%. So that's $1.5
million. So again, why go through this
process? Um, with that I'll I'll I'll
I'll flip forward um to the next couple
of pages which again are pretty much
consistent with what you saw uh at the
finance committee meeting. I can
certainly go over these in detail, but
suffice it to say that the when we
focused during the finance committee
meeting, uh, essentially with doing
these borrowings to provide $19 million
for general fund projects, 10 million
$10.3 million for sewer projects and
$9.1 million for water projects for a
grand total of a little under $ 38.5
million. Um, even though we're doing one
bond issue, they really have three
specific and concise components to to
fund the projects for those three uh
funds. The general fund, again, the
sewer fund, and the and the water fund.
Um, really the numbers are about the
same as we talked about. So, I I don't
know. I I'll hit the highlights here.
So, the general fund um we didn't want
to have any uh debt service impact in
the current year because, of course,
you've already adopted your budget.
though, uh, when you look at the
existing debt service numbers of $7.5
million for general fund, ultimately
you're going to have about about a
$900,000 increase in 2027, and that'll
be the the total impact um, as resulting
from these bonds. We're going to look at
the graphs. I think a lot of you like
the graphs better than the numbers. Uh,
looking over to sewer fund to provide
the $10.4 million for sewer projects.
you know, you're starting at existing
debt service of about 4 4.7 million uh
in
2026 uh next year uh because of an
increase that's already happening. The
total increase in sewer fund debt
service is going to be about
$150,000 and that's the full impact over
the next three years. Uh the water fund
uh for the $9.1 million of projects uh
the existing debt service is about $14
million a year. Um, debt service was
already going to go up, I'm going to
stress this, already going to go up, the
green the green highlighted number in
2026 by about a million dollars, it will
go up another almost million,
$985,000 again in 2028. That's really
the impact of this borrowing. So even
though you look at it and say, okay, by
2028, uh, Water Fund debt service is
going up by $2 million. again a million
of that was already going to happen
because of a previous borrowing. Um so
the again the incremental or additional
impact is about 985,000 from this
borrowing to provide the the 14 million.
Um so those again the numbers again
they're pretty much spot on of what you
saw during the finance committee
meeting. The next pages are all the
numbers we just talked about in a
graphical presentation. I think what
this shows best is uh how there will be
stepdowns or reduction in debt service
in outward years to either provide
budget flexibility going forward or
should you need to borrow additional
money in the future again is that budget
flexibility for additional borrowings.
So page three
um is the general fund the reds lines
being the existing annual debt service
and the green lines being the resulting
debt service after you do this
financing. So again, converting the
numbers I talked about on the first
page, uh in 2028,
uh your existing debt service is going
to go up about
$900,000. But after 3 years, it's
actually going to drop then $1.1 million
in
2030. Then you can see it'll drop again
in 2035 by another $1.4 million. Uh and
this financing is being done over a
20-year term. All of these terms when I
say that that this was financed over a
period of 20 years, it's to match the
useful life of the project. Obviously,
it's appropriate that you finance a
projects for not more than the useful
life of the project. Think of it like
your car. You don't finance your car for
10 years when you know you're going to
need a new one 5 years from
now. Uh the next page is the sewer fund.
Um this is to provide the 10 3 million
of projects. We're going to do this over
a 30-year term. Obviously, the the
projects are being done for the sewer
fund are much longer life. So, again,
it's appropriate to do it over a 30-year
term. Um there in 2026, you'll have the
increase of about
$150,000. Um out in 2035,
uh your the when the green line goes
down, your debt service is going to go
down about
$930,000. And then again in 2043, it'll
go down another $500,000. And lastly, in
2049, it would have got about $2.2
million. So again, should you need to
borrow in the future or otherwise, you
know, you have that budgetary capacity
or those reductions in your existing
debt service. Um, we'll talk about the
gold bars. That that is one thing that's
slightly different from when we were at
finance. Uh, Miss Campbell and I will
talk about
that. Um, lastly, uh, on page five, uh,
same type of presentation for the water
fund. Um the red bars again being the
existing annual debt service and the red
bars being uh I'm sorry the green bars
being after the 2025 bonds. Um if you
recall from our page one uh debt service
is going to go up already in 2026 by
about 1.1 million and go up another
million from this borrowing uh in 2028.
And you can see it'll stay there roughly
for the next uh 25 20 I'm sorry about 23
years. Uh this term of this component is
is a term of 25 years again to match
relatively match the useful life. Um the
gold bars um is not part of this bond
issue but this is what we talked about
when we were at finance committee
meeting.
Um there's an anticipation that with the
water transmission line, you're probably
going to be looking at uh a borrowing
hopefully with Penvest of about 41
million. Um the gold bars are just
layering that on top. Again, it's just
forward looking. That is not what you're
approving this evening, but you know, in
kind of the concept of looking forward
and transparency,
uh those are what you're expected to be
looking at with the water transmission
line project coming. Um, so that's
really where we stopped with the uh
discussion of the finance committee, the
numbers numerically on the first page
and the graphical presentations.
Everything else behind this is really
all the numbers. And when I say all the
numbers, there's a lot of numbers. I'm
happy to go over each one of these if
you'd like. Um, but really they're just
the numbers behind uh the graphical
presentations. Um, uh, page six is the
source and uses. Again, the the bond
issue will be
41,95,000 and that'll provide the $38.5
million of uh for for the projects. Um
I'll just highlight them. Page seven is
excuse me, is the general fund component
um of the new new bonds layering over
the existing debt service. Uh page eight
is the sewer fund
component. Uh page nine is the uh water
project component. And then page 10
really just brings all three components
together. It's really the entire bond
issue. Uh while we want to show you that
again really you got to look at this
almost as as if you're doing three
borrowings in one again to economize on
on the uh related costs in the process.
So
uh with that I'll certainly entertain
any questions. You've already introduced
the ordinance. Uh the ordinance among
other things uh would accept the the bid
or the proposal from RW Baird. Uh your
bond council uh Ronda Lord is here from
Sax and Stump and certainly if there's
any questions on the ordinance uh she
would entertain those. But uh with that
I will pause and see if there's any
questions or else you can move forward
with your vote. Can I get a copy of what
you Yeah. I just want to um share a
little bit more about the sewer graph. I
know Daryl had mentioned that we would
talk a little bit about that. So, um, he
had mentioned that during the the
finance committee meeting on March 3rd,
we had talked about the water fund um,
having a penved loan and overlaying with
that. Um, as we had some further
discussions with, uh, the public works
department. Um, after that meeting, we
decided to do the same thing with some
funding that we're going to need from
for the sewer fund. Um, uh, likely at
the be it will likely come at the
beginning of 2026. Um but we wanted to
just show that um in the in the graph as
well. So that's what the yellow bars
are. Um it's about 9.7 million that
we're anticipating would need to come
from Penvest. So again, it's not as part
of the bond for this evening. Um but
that's um that's that. And it's uh it's
three different projects. Nobody from
public works could be here this evening,
so I will read the projects, but um if
you have more uh detailed questions
about those, I will I will have to get
back to you. Um one of them is a new uh
clarifier. Um these are all for the
wastewater um facilities. Um one is um
some emergency work on our chlorination
facilities and the other is to improve
our screening handlings in um the south
train that we have.
Thank you both. And we had a pretty
thorough uh presentation during the
finance committee. Um thank you both for
the for the explanation. Um any council
comments? Councelor Amed. Thank you, Mr.
Vice President. Uh just one question um
and mainly just regard the general fund
projects. Um it says the the dated date
is 429. Is that when the funds will be
available to the city or when will these
funds be available to the city after the
passage of the ordinance?
Uh yes, your your assessment is
absolutely correct. Uh should you move
forward and authorize this this evening,
uh we would close on April the 29th and
you'd have the funds available for your
projects. Thank you. And this uh it's a
question probably for director Campbell.
Uh given that the 429 date is when the
funds will be available, when will we
see the schedule of the projects uh
start to happen and will council have to
re um will we have to revote on those um
ordinances or will the city keep a
breast of when these projects? Some of
these projects, you know, such as the
welcome center renovations, the the
lighting ballards replacing at Central
Market, the um the improvements to Ann
and Juna. I mean, some of these projects
are the community is waiting for. So,
when we be able to know to tell them
this is happening, yeah, we can come
back with reports. We don't need a new
ordinances when the projects start. So,
it would be a reporting out. Um, but we
can we can definitely do that. And I'll
just add I think the microphones do
sound low tonight, don't they? Um I'll
just add that
uh in June council will be uh presented
with a capital plan that is the um uh
looks out over the next 35 years. But
there will also obviously be shorter
term projects that will be on that and
there are time frames uh for delivering
those projects because we also need to
make sure that we are um spending bond
funds uh in an appropriate time period.
So that council will have a look at all
of the capital projects that are um
projected moving forward um in June. And
so that'll be a great time to ask those
questions. Councelor Med and also uh
regularly um you chair the public works
committee. No, John. Uh regularly ask
your committee uh leads uh for updates
and projects that represent those areas.
Uh thank you. And I look forward to
those updates. Thank you, Council Med.
Oh, there we go. Any other council
comments?
Any questions from the public?
Gardening Bird, South Street. Number
one, first I asked if I could get a copy
of what you gave. Number two, we have
this new um council chambers. We have
that up there. This isn't my first time
saying this. It would be very good for
the public if what you're looking at
could be displayed so we can also see
what you are looking at as far as the uh
report that he presented to you so we
can get a better understanding of what
he's talking about. And I think I've
asked this several times that if council
is given of information that that is
also displayed for the public so that we
can see. I think my question is about
the projects not coming out until June.
I am very concerned that we're borrowing
the money now and council is not really
aware of a timeline of projects. I think
uh even during the home rule we asked
for a 5-year capital campaigns that
would be going out. I don't think
there's enough information that I heard
receiving about what projects we're
spending. This is a
41,965. Is that what I heard?
41,95,000.
95,000 that they're asking for. I know
they said that the projects come to 38.
Is that correct? 38 million and some
dollars. Maybe an explanation on what
the extra $3 million is. Where that's
going would be helpful. I would like to
know what council thinks. How's that
going to affect the taxpayers that were
borrowing this money? Um, we did hear
that the bond rate was good. I was glad
to hear that the city was in a positive
mode. I'm really glad to hear that. Um I
think uh council needs to be able to
explain to the taxpayer what does this
really mean to us? I mean you're sitting
there and you're making those decisions.
We already heard that our water bill is
going to go up 14%. How does borrowing
this money affect
that? And how are we expecting to pay
that? We're looking over 30 years on
bond, which a lot of you will not be
sitting on council. Probably a lot of us
will not be sitting in the audience at
that time, but uh I think there needs to
be a more clear explanation to the
public and what we're doing here. Thank
you. Thank you, Miss B.
Just one point of reference, we did
receive a presentation when this was
initially introduced regarding the
projects that this will fund from the
general fund, water fund as well as
sewer fund. Um, also uh the debt service
was included in the projections when we
were doing forecasting and when we
passed the 2025 budget. Um just for some
clarification any additional public
comment.
Um one more for city council and the
finance committee here. Mr. If you could
just say your name and address. Of
course. John Minina 24 West Main Street
Strasburg Pennsylvania. um when you guys
were getting underwriters like for the
bidding process, did council or the
finance committee kind of check or do
their due diligence with any of these
banks and if they're scaling back their
DEI policies or anything like that? You
know, with how the country is weaving
away from some of those important
issues, we want to make sure that we're
not um paying out banks that are kind of
going away from what the city what's
important to the city. So, is that
something you guys did from a due
diligence standpoint looking at who's
coming to the table with their bids? Uh,
and if they're stepping away cuz a lot
of major institutions and banks um have
kind of scaled away or cowardly backed
away from DEI. So, I'm just asking if
that's something you guys have uh taken
in consideration at that. Thank
you. I know there's a specific process
when it comes to the bidding. Director
Campbell, do you want to elaborate a
little bit on that or Daryl?
Um there yeah there's a there's a
process that goes through the bond
auction. We don't typically review the
policies for for banks. Yeah.
And it's sorry correct me if I'm wrong.
It's typically required for us to go to
the lowest interest rate that's
presented. That's Yeah. Right. Yeah.
And just for my curiosity, if council
ever did want to uh know about specific
policies that any financial institution
does bid on, is there a way for us to
find that information out?
Yeah, I mean, yeah, we could look at the
bank policies, but we don't typically do
that in the bond auction. So, and I can
also just say that um much of our
investments are are uh with banks are
through the pension boards and the
pension boards are not controlled uh by
council or even myself although I serve
as um president of the pension boards.
They are made up of retirees and active
um uh employees um who are focused on
their retirement funds and returns. We
have had conversations regarding these
issues in the past and there's very um
there there's a lot of a lot of people
on the pension boards who have a lot of
different points of view about this.
Thank you for the
clarification.
Any additional questions or comments
from the public?
Okay, Susie, do I have to say it again?
Uh, yes, please. Susie Gomez, North 100
block of North Reservoir Street. So,
while you guys are looking at projective
reports and planning for your futures
ahead, um,
and, uh, home rule is basically a
positive view in the city because
taxpayers are the only ones that are
going to be burdened with this bond.
Okay. There's grants that come up, you
know, projects you have mentioned,
Ahmad, um, projects for Ann Street and
Juniata. We know that those projects
were already paid for. Izzy secured a
$500,000 grant for those projects. And
then uh January 20 of 24, there was a
construction company that came with a
presentation to us at the school in
Washington and shared that they were
already paid
$450,000 on that project. So, um, what
you were mentioning has nothing to do
with this bond that they're discussing
as far as projects are concerned for
Southeast.
Um the other thing is um I just want to
mention that as you continue to burden
us as taxpayers in this city to look at
a bond that is going to be secured for
the next 2530 years that our children
would have to pay for because as the
mayor mentioned she's already on the
president board. She has her future
plans and it's well established. That's
why you guys ignore us because it's not
what we want. There's no common interest
here. There's no commonwealth. There's
just socialism in this
administration. It goes back and forth.
We know that $9.1 million was given to
the water system for a grant along with
the $7 million. You know what I mean?
There's money pouring in from grants.
There's other means of grants that can
be established so that we can pay a debt
and not go more further into debt and
deprive the people, especially our
children, while you secure your futures.
Shameful. Any additional questions or
comments from the public?
Patrick, excuse me, Patrick Thorath,
Hebring Street. Um, I just want to say
it's embarrassing the political slight
of hand you pulled when that gentleman
asked about which banks and financial
institutions uh you're allowing to
you're collaborating with. These are
institutions that cause untold suffering
across the world that are collaborating
with our
fascist government in Washington and you
just you just ignore it. You just brush
it away as if it doesn't matter. Thank
you.
Uh my name is Brian Nelson. Uh I got a
little too close there. Sorry. Um so my
name is Brian Nelson. I live off of
Columbia Avenue. um right outside um
Lancaster City and um so I I completely
understand um kind of your guys's point
um when you're talking about um you know
the bonds and stuff like that, but did
you guys do any due diligence at all?
And I understand the bank thing too, but
I do hope that you guys do consider in
the future actually looking into who
you're doing business with. I think that
that would be a good practice. So maybe
that's something you guys can look at in
the future. But um in terms of like the
bonds and stuff, did you guys do any due
diligence to find out if there were any
other sources of funding for these
projects or did you just jump straight
into let's get a loan? So um I just want
to know kind of what that process looked
like for you guys and did you figure out
could we get a grant? Could we you know
maybe use some federal funding? What
options did we have before we burden our
citizens with 30 with like 31 or sorry
40 whatever it was millions of dollars
of debt that gets paid onto the
taxpayer. No, we're we're paying you. So
I mean I I would hope you guys can
figure that out.
Yeah, happy to add some context.
Typically whenever these projects come,
I know the administration works very
hard and the team at city hall works
very hard to find other funding
opportunities. Many of our projects are
grant funded. Um a good example uh which
I think was mentioned earlier with the
Ann and Juniata Streetscape project. Um
we did receive $450,000 in the Keystone
Communities Grant. Um but that still
leaves
$950,000 unfunded which will be funded
by the bond. So uh this um
administration I know does work hard to
look for other funding sources to try to
um alleviate some of the pressure on the
taxpayer. But good question. anything
that I'm missing, Director Campbell,
with that?
I think I think you mentioned most of
it. I would just say that u many of the
projects in the project list do have
grant funding associated with them, but
they often require some sort of match.
And so that's what's the what's listed
in the projects.
Thank you.
And I'll just add one more thing to that
which is that we are under uh
significant and I'll be talking a little
bit about this in my remarks um
regulatory pressures in which we need to
meet certain milestones um to address
water quality and um uh other issues. Uh
please also recognize that our water and
sewer systems serve customers in and
outside of the city and that um when we
borrow funds um there are a variety of
ways to finance uh and um and that
usually is borrowing through bonds um
through going out to banks and getting
um a low bid and or uh using the state
revolving loan program. uh that is
operated through Penvest is another
option. Uh so the the borrowing for
these size projects is a significant
infrastructure project. So one that
we're working on right now is a 42-in
main replacement that is running 13
miles u from the Suscoana River into the
city. That's approximately it's on the
verge of probably $und00 million between
design uh and construction cost as well
as material cost. Uh just to give you a
scope of the size and scope of projects
that we're talking about. So um I'm also
particularly proud that we have
um 70 $80 million of um grant fundings
under grant funding under management.
And I will also just say that um I
expect us to not have that opportunity
uh because federal grants are drying up.
Not really.
Thank you. Any additional questions or
comments from the public?
Right.
Mr. Harris,
I think Miss Darlene would like to I'm
sorry. M you have a comment. I just
wanted to say that I believe that I
understand the bonds and I understand
for the water and everything, but I
think when we talk about these other
projects of parks and everything to
actually get a bond to be able to, you
know, do these parks, we have to come up
with a better solution. We're talking
about 25 years. You know, how many times
are the parks going to be redone? How
many times has the Milbour Park been
done since you were on council? Let's
just take the eight years. And I mean to
say this for 25 years. I do and I agree
with what's happening with the water and
the sewer, but I think these other
projects, we do not need to be getting a
bond to do these projects because that's
on taxpayers. And there's got to be
other ways to finance them. And I think
that should be taken in consideration
when talking about how much money we're
trying to borrow now.
Mr. Harris.
Yes, Mr. Vice President on the on the
motion to amend.
Mr. Matt, I Mrs. Royer. I Mr. Please. I
Mr. Gr. I Miss
Mr. H. I
Mr. And now on the amended bill,
Mr. M. I
Mr. Row. I Mrs. Please. I Mr. Hi, Miss
Diaz. None. Mr. H. I.
Great. Uh we'll move on to resolution
number administration resolution number
182025. A resolution of the council of
the city of Lancaster authorizing the
disposal of certain obsolete records in
conformity with the retention and
disposition schedule for records of
Pennsylvania municipalities.
Second. We have a motion and a second.
Councelor Diaz.
Yes. Um Lancaster introduced a
resolution number 18 2025 which will
authorize the disposal of certain
obsolete police records. This action
aligns with retention and disposition of
schedule of records for Pennsylvania
municipalities as outlined in the
municipal records manual. The city has
previously committed to the following
schedule through resolution 7 back in
1975. The resolution allows police
bureau records to supervise the disposal
of specific outdated records ensuring
compliance with state guidelines for
municipal records and management. And
for those that don't know, um it's
basically citations like traffic,
non-traffic records from 20 to 21,
animal compliance, um basically incident
reports, records from 21 to 22,
abandoned vehicles incident reports
records from 2018 to 22, permits and
related application, handicap
application records from 2018 to 2021,
noting that these application expired
December the 31st. first and let's see
all let's see it was issued um 2021
application apply expired on December
31st 2021 and that is it. Thank you
councelor Diaz. Any questions or
comments from councel
from the public?
Jessica Lopez, Lancaster City. Um,
I I don't believe that at a time where
we're asking for transparency from our
police department and getting
gaslighting and getting lied to and not
giving evidentiary support to the things
we're asking, we should be throwing away
police records.
I don't think that we can trust you
enough to tell us exactly what you're
throwing away. And I believe that this
issue is out of touch right now and
should be tabled until the impeding
issue is actually taken care of. Y'all
shouldn't be throwing nothing out in
that police station right now.
How are we supposed to trust yous when
you literally just heard everything that
went down in here week after week and
want to sit up there and be like, "We
should throw stuff
away." If I clean my house right before
a raid, they're going to be digging in
my trash looking for the
evidence. What? What? Where's the
disconnect here?
I didn't even know this was on the
agenda, but like where's the disconnect
here? Do you not live around
here? I know for a fact some of you do.
What do you not
see? Our kids go to school together. You
live on the same blocks. You're drinking
the same water. What are you not getting
about the issues? And why do we think
that laughing in our faces and promoting
things like this is okay?
Y'all didn't sit down and be like
they're going to not trust us to do this
right
now.
Anybody? Oh, Mr. President. Um uh I will
uh say that uh this was tabled at the
last meeting. Um given the the uh the
discussions we were having at the last
meeting, I thought it was most
appropriate to wait until uh Chief
Mendes or the mayor was uh available to
answer any questions. The mayor is here
this evening. So that's why I uh moved
to uh bring it back on the agenda
tonight because we do have the ability
to get questions answered. I appreciate
that, Council. Now, so then the question
is, where's the real list of what you'll
be getting rid of? And how do you really
prove that that's what you are getting
rid of? We don't have transparency from
our police department. We can't go in
there whenever we please. That's a fact.
It's not a public
space. But so you can just do whatever
you want, throw away whatever you want,
and we're just supposed to trust and
believe this. I feel like I don't know
who else stands with me on this one. It
needs to be tabled
[Music]
again. I comment on that.
I second that. This is an extremely
tonedeaf thing to put forward to us at
this moment in time. Um I think it's
disgusting that we would even talk about
it. Um, I hope that each and every
single one of you uh votes nay cuz this
is the kind of thing that, you know, we
talked about a public review board and
this is the kind of thing that a public
review board should be looking at. Not
the police force, not you guys, us.
Because it's ridiculous that, you know,
we we keep talking about these issues
with police violence and police violence
all over the country. And yet you are
here talking about what 21 22 that's
only 3 years ago. That's not long
enough. They they they've been commit
they've been doing police violence for
the past few for like decades. I don't
want those records gone. I want each and
every single one of them held
accountable for what they've done.
That's right. This this like each and
every single one of you needs to vote
no. Just flat out. I don't even want it
tabled. I want it gone. I want a public
review commission. They're the ones that
should be making these decisions. Not
the police, not us. I don't trust the
police force. They've shown over the
over their last statements we cannot
trust them. Why do you think I would
trust them to throw something in the
shredder?
I can't I can't even trust them with the
evidence that they gather from
somebody's home, let alone the evidence
that's sitting right in their own halls.
So, I'm sorry. I'm just flustered right
now because it's baffling. I I came here
cuz I saw this on the agenda. I saw it
and this is why I'm here because this is
ridiculous. And you guys need to vote no
or I hope that each and every single one
of you gets a challenge for your seat. I
don't think that you deserve a seat on
that council if you vote for this.
So again, this council creates
commission of black and brown affairs
related to police brutality. This was
related to police brutality. You're
telling me that in 2020 you had
established this commission? Why are we
here then? Why are we here? Are you
lying to us, Jamie? Now, in in regards
to these records being thrown away, we
all know that these little citations and
everything wants to make you guys look
better so that your citation can
disappear, so that Izzy's citation can
disappear, so that Amanda BK's citation
can disappear. There's a lot more to
this picture. We're not idiots. Okay, so
just like Jessica said, why should we
not table? It doesn't make sense.
Your records can go away, but we can't
get justice. Crazy.
Councelor Diaz, would you like to
reiterate the explanation around the
resolution and what it entails in
disposing or what records is disposing
of? Just for clarity for the public. For
clarity, as Jessica
said, we would need to speak to the
mayor because she is the one that um
authorizes what the police are going to
do. So, um I'm happy to to speak to this
uh this resolution to destroy uh safety
records as uh councelor Diaz walked
through our first citations, animal
complaints, abandoned vehicles, permits,
and related applications. It is the
purview of council uh to make a
determination about whether or not these
records are uh disposed of. I will also
say that this is in keeping with um
policies and practices that are used um
uh per the municipal records manual
which governs all of the municipalities
across Pennsylvania. Um I also
understand that um that there is a
feeling in the room that this feels like
why are you talking about destroying
records um at this particular moment. I
understand and I hear that. I would also
say that this is a pretty regular thing
that happens. We bring it to council as
a matter of transparency and in mean in
ensuring that we are following the
municipal records manual. This
recommendation is submitted by the
record supervisor who is a civilian
staff member at the police bureau and
council may decide what they would like
to do related to uh resolution. Um we
have
um we have these records. They're there
from five to 8 years ago and you can
decide what happens to them.
That's not Thank you, Mayor Sarachi. If
if I may, Mayor, is there a right to
know, which I doubt because it's a
Pennsylvania law, for the community to
look at those records, which I'm not
sure if that's possible, but I'm not
sure either. If somebody wants to see
these records, um, uh, they could submit
a right to know request to review the
records. uh that would need to go
through the right to know process and
that's available to anyone in the room
or beyond.
Thank you. Can I just 30 more seconds
please?
Um again I reiterate there was a etc at
the end of that other related records.
So other related records could really be
anything. And at a pivotal time where
we're looking for our future mayor to
take a stand, you have a position to say
no, we don't trust it. And until you
find a way to make us feel comfortable,
we have a
$76.8 million police budget. Those
records have a place to be stored. We
pay for it.
hold on to them, build trust in your
community, and then figure out what to
do with the paperwork later. That's my
suggestion on that because I recently
watched somebody go through the right to
know process and they were denied the
body cam footage they asked for and
forced into a 30-day extension because
you don't want to give up the body cam
footage. We can't trust the police
department and the right to know act
isn't in place to protect us either. So
who is
youth? Say no. It's that easy.
If I may. Um, councelor councelor Diaz,
I think that what the community is
talking about is that they do want a
citizens law enforcement advisory
committee. And by putting by placing
that, this is going to give everybody
the opportunity to look at records like
them. And I did bring this up to several
people in the community. I forget the
young lady's name, but also to Susie.
and I spoke directly to um city council
members that I know in
Hammersburg. If I mean if the community
wants to hold on it, let's vote. Let's
vote on it. Um but I think this is
something that I could make a motion on
um at a later date for you for the bill
of 9080 2020 from Harrisburg to see if
it's something that could fit the
community. And of course the solicitor
and the mayor will have to look at it as
well. Councelor Diaz, just for
clarification, we are discussing
resolution number 18, 2022. That is
correct. Yeah. Not another We're not
introducing another bill at this moment.
No, at this point.
Any other council? Um, when I made the
motion to table this resolution at our
last meeting, um, it was under the
impression that we were going to have a
report requested by council. Uh, and
since it is not this evening, uh, and
we're hoping that it will be in the
April legislative agenda, I will make a
motion to table this resolution until
that report. Second,
we have a motion to table the
resolution. Did I hear you correctly? To
the next committee meeting, council med.
Uh, yes. To the April legislative
agenda. So, that would be at the April
committee meeting to be reintroduced. To
be introduced and we have a
second. Any question, comments on the
motion to table?
Public comment.
Sorry, did you say you're waiting on a
report and you're hoping you have that
report by the April meeting? I didn't
quite understand that. Uh yes, at the
last meeting of council, uh I made a
motion to table this resolution that was
passed unanimously. Uh I made that
motion um uh in thinking that the report
that was requested would happen this
evening. Uh and given that the community
has requested to table it further, I
will make that motion to table it until
the April legislative agenda uh and we
hope to have a report from the public
safety committee and Chief Mendes at
that uh committee. And if the report's
not given, you would not bring it
forward. Is that correct? We would
revisit it at that time. Okay.
And I'll I'll just add that uh it is it
was my understanding that the report to
council by Chief Mendes was for the
April committee meeting and Chief Mendes
will be here for that meeting.
Thank you.
Thank you Amed. I really appreciate
that. And I just want to second uh the
bill number 82020 to be adopted and
looked at by council
respectfully. I'm just reiterating that.
You guys each have it.
Any additional public comment,
Mr. Harris?
On the motion to table and to clarify
this is until the uh the April 8th
meeting. Correct. And we will revisit it
at that time. Thank you,
Mr. M. I Mr. Roy. I Mr. Please. I Miss
Gra. I Miss I Mr. Hurst. Hi.
That concludes our legislative agenda
this evening. Um, next we'll move into
our second public comment period. Uh,
this is open for comment about issues
not on the agenda. Uh, duration of
comments are limited to 3 minutes.
Jessica Lopez, Lancaster City. Um, and
this of course is about what we all
really came here for. So, let me start
by saying I echo the members of the
community that already
approached and spoke today, but trust
and believe, we expected the reaction
that we got at that press conference. We
expected them to gaslight. We expected
them to lie. And our community still
waited. We did not harass you in the
process. We waited for that footage to
only be
denied for use for the police department
to hide under the fact that there was
juveniles in the videos. So then I ask,
if it's because of the juveniles in the
videos, why were the parents denied the
footage? If it's to protect the children
in the videos, why deny the parents the
body cams? Why make them wait a whole
another month to find out what really
happened to their children that night?
This is
disgusting. This is
disgusting. Like, and I mean it in all
serious. It's not an exaggeration when I
say it. My kids are two times bigger
than those boys and they're 15 and 16.
If your cops are scared of those boys,
they're going to be terrified of my
sons. And I promise you, it's not a
threat. Should I ever be one of my sons,
I'm not coming to city council with my
issue. And that's the real problem.
That's where things are going to get.
People can't trust our members to take
care of this situation right now. to
allow them to to attach those kids to
guns the way they did and criminalize
them the way they did and be like,
"Oh, let's get upset because we put in
so much work in our police department.
If you take out your trash this week,
you still have to take it out next
week. New people come, new problems
arise, and you still have to handle
them.
In 2020, a situation transpired in
downtown Lancaster. The city
rioted, right? And youth needed somebody
to blame. I went to jail for 10 months
so you could tell people to stop
throwing frozen water bottles at your
police station. And guess what? Nobody
did it since. If you don't penalize the
officers that are doing this, those
other officers that are learning
underneath them are going to think it's
okay to do
this. So, stop saying, "Oh, we can't put
him on administrative duties." You
can't. No, you can't fire
him, but you can keep him inside his
cage.
And all of you know that this is not
whether it's through federal lawsuit or
through things j and hushtouched and
clinkedked up. Hatfield's been an issue.
It's not new. Miss, I'm going to ask 30
more seconds, please. Yes, sir. It's not
new. These are 20 plus senior officers
that were taught racist policing ways
and are embedded in them. This is
conditioning.
We all know about racist conditioning.
So, as you continue to perpetuate this
cycle and capitalize for us instead of
protecting us, and I have to say use,
cuz you are who I talk to. And until
y'all change this, it's going to keep
doing this this policing for profit
that's going on around here. Why use
bleed us for all our tax dollars? What
do you think you're going to have
left again? You can't fire him. Fine.
keep him inside the building and stop
saying you can't do that because you
can. You make the
ordinances. So y'all made the ordinance
with the that the bike refractor issue
came from. You oversee the mayor who
oversees the chief of police who
oversees the officers. You can tell him
keep your job. We'll continue to pay
you. Sit at this desk.
Is that is that against the the
So that's against the agreement we have
with the union. Miss Lopez, I just want
to maintain uh comments for 3 minutes,
please. Yeah, but the mayor just said
something. So I was trying to hear what
she was saying. So yes, that's against
what the union contract is. What I would
say is that a lot of the things that are
being discussed, there are real
limitations and we are talking past each
other. And so I hear what the demands
are. There's not been a conversation
that's been had outside of this
chambers. And I'm not sure that anything
that I say tonight is going to be
helpful to this audience at this moment.
It's not about what you say, it's about
what you do. And I understand
that's the thing. It's not about what
you are talking about or what I'm
talking about. It's about what you just
do. Look the demands that are being made
there there are limitations on city
councils. There's limitations. There's
lots of limitations there. There is so
is it a facade and we have city council
members and a mayor that's supposed to
oversee a department that really
oversees itself. Let me just tell you
I'm going to let sorry just point of
order real quick. We'll let the mayor
respond and then we're going to conclude
this point. Thank
you mayor. Sorry.
Um, it is clear that we need to have a
better and shared understanding of
police practices and protocols and the
legal constraints that are overseeing
the functions of the police bureau.
Chief Mendes was asked to come and speak
to council and he will come to talk
about use of force training and to
answer other questions that council has.
We um
have many conversations in the past
about some of the things that are being
requested and I have had
the responsibility to be honest that the
demands that are being asked for cannot
be met through the things that are being
requested or demanded from the community
because there are systems beyond this
these bodies that control what is
available in terms of oversight. I will
also say that the police bureau in
contrast to what you may perceive
related to the bureau right
now is very different than when I got
here in 2018.
There has been a tremendous amount of
work done. They have put in an an amount
of effort especially over the last years
led by Chief Mendes that I am very proud
of. And that's why you're taking offense
instead of addressing the situation. I
understand you put in work to change the
department. Yes, you fired a few people.
You did this. You did that. Well,
there's another issue that has arised
and it needs addressed. It doesn't need
a constant reminder that you've done
things in the past. Like I said, you
have to keep taking out the trash, the
limitations, whatever the case may be.
Maybe you do need to have a conversation
with your community and fully explain
who you put in place here because you
are no longer in place. Apparently,
Miss in order to be fair, I'm I'm
walking off. Thank you.
Good evening. I'm Heidi Sherk, 100 block
of East Lemon Street. I have two very
boring questions. Um, what happened to
item B on the agenda?
Did we miss that? I'm sorry. Uh, that
was administration number bill, I'm
sorry, bill 2, 2025. I mentioned at the
top of the meeting that that was going
to be removed from the agenda this I
missed that. Okay.
And then my my second
sorry my mic question or comment is
earlier during the um the first public
comment it seemed apparent that there's
a time when the person at the podium
asks questions or makes a statement and
maybe at the closure of their statement
is when you respond but it didn't it
didn't seem like that was explained to
the person at the podium. So, I was just
wondering if that's something in the
future either Mr. Royo, whoever's in
that seat or Mr. Harris can just explain
like we will not respond to you and your
questions until you finish your comment.
So, just a a little um note on that.
Thank you. Thank you.
Hi, I'm Jenny Calibri, 500 block of
North Street. Uh my comment is
specifically for Mayor Sarra. I think
it's deeply embarrassing to be a grown
woman who took an elected position and
sits on this board and smirks at the
people who are coming to you with valid
concerns. You are sitting there and you
are defending the police and you are
saying we have come so far from 2018.
That's probably true. I don't know the
specifics. That's probably true. We also
abolished slavery, which used to be a
system that was held up by the law, and
abolished that. Do you want a cookie for
it? Do you want a cookie for doing the
right thing for the people of this
community and black and brown people and
talking to your constituents in such a
condescending way?
It is not hard to take one step back and
have some humility and recognize that
okay there might be systems in place but
number one skirting around them does not
make the public feel safety or trust in
you as an elected official and number
two systems can change you can advocate
for them look at Philly look at what
Philly just did I don't remember the
name of the organization I think it's
like CPOC but their police review board
whatever that's called They took steps
just in January to change how they work
with the public to defend people because
the systems in place before were not
working. So I truly truly hope that you
feel proud of the work that you have
done because you have done work good
work but you have a long way to go. And
I truly hope that the next person who
takes your place has a little bit more
humility and doesn't smirk at the people
who come before them with concerns about
teenagers who are brutalized at the
hands of the police, which is not the
first time this has happened in
Lancaster. And we have not made progress
since 2018, 2019,
2020. Thank you.
Okay. Uh, good evening. My name is
Oakley Bascarino. Uh, I have to
apologize for the deviation of topic,
but um, I'm coming here representing
Pennsylvania College of Art and Design
and their entire uh, over 400 student
body. What excited many students about
enrolling in this Lancasterbased art
school was the artistic world that
surrounded it and the creative life that
flourishes in this city. However, a rise
of tariffs and general pricing has made
businesses shy away from reaching out to
artists. In suit, the rise of artificial
intelligence due to its cheapness and
accessibility diminishes Lancaster's
creative vision and neglects
opportunities for PCAD's population. As
students working tooth and nail toward
success, we came here to remind you that
PCAD is your creative pantry. There are
over 400 unique artists that are seeking
the chance to get their hands on
client-based work. And as our careers
are being threatened, we wish to become
more an option for creative businesses
and branding needs. I'm going to take
time to circle back to AI, the very tool
that has taken jobs from over 26% of
illustrators internationally. According
to the Society of Authors, 43% of
artists seeing a decrease in their
income because of it. The International
Monetary Fund also claimed that 40% of
jobs aside from the art field are
actively occupied by artificial
intelligence. Although with this intent
to amplify productivity, it has actively
proven to cause significant job
displacements. These statistics are
exemplified in journal in the journal
the market for example which is facing
nasty competition with chat GBT the
famous AI writing assistant that almost
half of college students nationwide
abuse for their assignments and
coursework. One in five students in
America use chat GBT to write essays.
According to the Pew Research Center,
70% of students nationally uh use it to
facilitate research. With this tool
growing to take up the forefront of
education and industry, the journalism
market has faced lower wages and minimal
job opportunities. While AI produces
work that lacks human understanding,
Lancaster's community of being a visual
arts and small business emporium is also
at risk of similar happenings. It may be
cheaper for business owners to generate
AI artwork, but you take away the human
touch that your branding designs and
illustrations need. On top of that, you
strip a job, freelance, or internship
opportunity from a selection of over 400
growing artists right here in Lancaster
currently attending PCAD. Students who
are paying over $100,000 to deem
themselves qualified to make that work
for you. Other job markets will crumble
following the arts if AI isn't rejected.
All of this to say this is a cry for
help. A plea from student creatives who
are preparing to step foot into these
attacked industries. Lancaster's unique
uniqueness has been excuse me has been
created by the hands of creatives for
years. There are students here eager to
utilize their creativity for you for
free. And as a city that encourages such
entrepreneurial ideas, we ask that you
seek out our passionate students for
your design needs. Lancaster is human
art and as a resident of Lancaster we
ask you help this mission thrive. Thank
you for your time.
Daryl Legacy 100 block of North Mary. Um
I'm sure that the finance people were
probably not looking forward to this
today but this one speaks to you at
least a little. Uh we're lucky that
Moody's when they raided us didn't take
into account the fact that if the police
keep acting with impunity, we're going
to have multi-million dollar lawsuits
that our city is going to be paying and
we're going to deserve it. All right. So
far, we've been lucky um that they are
mostly brutalizing poor people and brown
people. Someday they're going to get a
rich kid. They're going to get someone
that knows a really good lawyer or
there's going to be a lawyer that says
this is a slam dunk case and we're going
to be paying millions, tens of millions
of dollars to people because of the
police. So, if you don't care about any
of these other things, I realize there's
things you cannot do. You can call them
out. Instead of standing with them at
their press conference, you can say,
"No, I will not stand with you. I do not
agree with you. Maybe I can't fire you,
but I wish I
could." And I think even if you just
care about the money part, this is a
serious problem that we are not solving.
We're not even trying to solve it. And I
just find myself flabbergasted by the
fact that we cannot even do the simplest
thing like a review board. Like that is
the bare minimum. And so I really really
ask this city council to please put that
on the agenda for the next
meeting. Thank
you. Taylor Raymond, 500 block of St.
Joseph Street. Um,
so it's my understanding that the reason
the body cam footage uh isn't being
released is because there were minors
involved
um uh and that their privacy needs to be
protected. I understand that. I don't
want to know the identities of people
that have gone through something like
that. Something that can be done is you
can blur the faces of people uh and that
will help protect their identity. um and
will uh satisfy part of the demands that
have been made for uh for the footage to
be released to us. Um, additionally, uh
this is a separate thing.
Um the uh last meeting that I was at, it
was mentioned that there uh had been
lead pipes. Um was that for the entirety
of Lancaster City?
Uh I can answer your question if you can
want to wrap up your comments. Okay. Um
if it is for the entirety of the city, I
never received it in the southwest end.
Neither did any of the people living in
my apartment building. Um and I just
need to know why that is. That's all.
Absolutely. Um you should have received
notice with your utility bill or your
water bill. Um the city is currently
undergoing a lead a lead pipe inventory
uh to see where there potentially are
lead pipes um throughout the city, but
you should have received that. If not,
talk to you offline on where you can
find more information about that. Vice
President, uh can I also clarify that I
believe that in the case of a renter um
it went to both the the landlord and the
renters. That correct? Yes. Okay. Yes.
And I this and also if you can just
confirm with me your address later, I
will make sure that we follow up. Um and
I just wanted to say that um we are
talking about there's 50,000 lines. We
have to have two forms of verification
uh for the state uh for those lines.
Right now um we have identified about 1%
of the lines. Uh we are much more
concerned in the city of Langster
related to lead paint than we are to
lead pipes, but this is a federal
mandate. This is part of um some of the
costs that you heard about related to
water just a little bit ago. Uh and so
um happy to follow up. And apartment
buildings are a little more complicated,
but you only have one meter coming in.
And if we've already identified it,
we're not following up with all the
renters.
Thank you for that clarification on the
step piece. Thank you.
Uh Brian Nelson, um right off of
Columbia Avenue, Bandian Circle Drive.
Um so, uh I understand that we talked a
lot about um the failures of our police
department and the failures of the mayor
on terms of holding them accountable,
but um I wanted to ask a question for
each and every single one of you sitting
there right now. Um with uh ICE going
through communities deporting
individuals who are um not even
undocumented, you know, they were
deported because of their tattoos. Um,
some were even American, born here. Um,
and then you also have the Trump
administration just going through and
cutting federal funding for multiple
programs throughout the country that,
you know, provide necessary food and
housing for people who lack the
resources to do so. I want to hear from
each and every single one of you what
your commitment is over the next four
years to do something about this and
what you guys plan to do in that
position that you hold so dearly. What
are you going to do to make sure that
Lancaster remains safe and remains a
bastion for those who come here to work
and pay taxes and live just according to
their values. So what is your commitment
to that right now?
If I may, um, Vice President, I'd like
to, um, answer that question. Councelor
Diaz, just wrap up public comment. Can
you hold your comments until council
comments later? Okay. Thank you. Next
speaker, please.
Hi. So, Beta Rosa, um, Lancaster
Township. I just had a question, I
guess, for the mayor and the other
counselors if they would like to answer.
um what is in your power in terms of
this policing and what we're talking
about? What is in your power? What are
you able to do? Um in terms of Mayor
Sarra, I've seen you the past couple of
years address the public. I've even seen
you cry in public about the policing and
how much it's affected you. But in terms
again of your advocacy for your
constituents, how does that translate
over? because then when you do a public
press conference aligning yourself with
the police, it doesn't really align my
trust or transparency to want to work
with you. I know your term is ending, so
I'm sure you don't really care about us
that much, but at least that's how it
feels. Um, and I did say Lancaster
Township, but the water, the sewer, the
police, they all operate within the
township. Am I correct in saying that?
No. So, you have your own police
department. Okay. So, the Lancaster City
Police didn't come through my
neighborhood then and that's not them
going around. Okay. Thank you.
Next speaker, please.
Uh John Tolen, first and only block of
Wise A. Um, Mayor Sarra, uh, your
response to just Lopez was kind of vague
and I think that most people here would
like to know what the actual limitations
are and if there's some kind of town
hall we could have so that we could
actually go through what the proper
channels could be to have some kind of
actual action happen when it comes to
maybe the death duty or what we would
need to do in order to put pressure on
the police department to fire specific
specific police officers or why can't we
do that? Like you're being very vague
and I think giving us more detail would
kind of help.
[Music]
Hi. Um my name is Taylor. I Taylor
Nurine. I live in Manheim Burough, but I
work here in the city and have been put
through uh the legal system here. Um,
Mayor Sarra, you're staying on your
mayoral time here in Lancaster will be
remembered and laughed at. You stood in
2020 in the streets, got your photos,
and it did nothing. The police lied to
us then and you they lied to you and
then you lied to us and during that
time. So, what are they hiding now? and
who are we
protecting? We stood here two weeks ago
and every council member stood with the
community and said it was disturbing and
disgusting what we witnessed. And we all
waited patiently while you were on
vacation, which you're allowed to do. I
all imply implore us to do that. But
then when you got back, we were
expecting or hoping that maybe you would
denounce the actions that you also
witnessed in those videos. But no, you
stood and did the most disgusting move
by blaming the community, families, and
the children involved. And are we
willing to accept this type of policing
for our children for the crime of bike
no bike reflectors and lights and
pulling fire alarms? And now you sit
here and dismiss us when we are making
demands and trying to rebuild the trust
in the community to have transparency
and accountability which everyone seems
to want for us and to continue to work
together but then it's like just shot
down and it doesn't seem like you are
willing to do that with us. Um, and
that's just really like this stage like
it's just it just sits with me. At the
same time, we are going to continue to
put children who we're riding bikes
through the legal system to make like to
make a stance um and continue forward
with this. And I think as we see uh when
the city wants to make an example of
someone, they will do so. Thank you.
with them cops.
Any additional public comment
and I just I just want to say for the
end
um lead paint is the job of
housing. Lead pipes are the job of the
city. if you would face if you would
focus on the area because it was already
known before Denine you took office that
the sewer plant was
compromised 30 years ago we were in our
last 10 years the solutions were well
overdue but your concern was more about
equitable solutions with long-term
effects officer Hatfield
field has multiple encounters since
1989. Okay. His excessive force for
decades has many people in this city
frightened. And with this incident that
happened on these young children because
they were children, 14, 15, they're
children. It's unacceptable.
It should be condemned. This officer
should not be on the force. He has no
self-control. It is clearly evident on
that video that his
training. I don't understand how you can
pat him on the back and say, turn it
around and look at these children and
say you're the blame. It's
unacceptable. your ignorance to us as
taxpayers. I mean, it's going to go down
in centuries as to who you are, but
again, you're going to be the president
of the home rule, so you're already
positioned. Yeah. Sucks.
Sorry.
Next speaker, please.
Okay. Hello. My name is uh Betty Jones,
Southand Concerned Neighbors. Um, my
address is 222 South. Uh, I'm calling I
mean I'm here to talk about uh the issue
with
trash. Okay. On
211 the I mean our block I should I mean
our area from the 100 block down to the
400 block we receive
citations for trash that was blown. It's
not something that we did. Mother Nature
blew the trash and all of a
sudden I call I got a citation. So I
called and the person that I spoke with
told me they got a phone call from
someone talking about the trash and the
debris. So all of everyone from the 100
block to the 400 block got a $25
citation first. I called them and I told
them I went outside and I'm like, "Okay,
what's trash?" I picked up um there was
a pizza box. I have a tree in front of
my house. So, there was tree break the
limbs and everything was on the on the
ground plus our property at 259 South An
Street. Okay. They came and they cleaned
it up.
We have pictures to show that we went by
there today and there's trash boxes and
everything out there again. Okay. So, I
along with everyone else, we have the
$25 plus the two
$200 fine. I told the lady, I'm not
paying it. I'm going to fight it because
it's not something that I did. I went
outside and I seen whatever that was
there. I picked it up. I'm sorry. If you
look at public comment happening at the
moment if you don't mind. Okay. She have
the pictures. She have the pictures to
show you because I was talking since I'm
talking. I wanted you to
see. That's the reason why she's there.
Okay. So,
um I just wanted to um talk about that
because I don't usually get up and say
something, but with something they're
charging me want to charge me $200 for a
cleanup. And if you look at the
pictures, you'll see that what they
picked up wasn't nothing. It was
branches that fell off my tree. The city
would not give me permission to cut the
tree down. So therefore, the branches
are falling down. And when they're
little branches, they're not big big
stuff. And I I just don't see what they
she called she told me that they came
and um someone cleaned something up for
picking up a box or whatever. you're
gonna charge me $200 for that? I mean, I
could have picked that up myself, which
I didn't even see anything, but if you
guys look at the pictures, you'll see
there wasn't nothing like that. And I
did call I did call down and I talked to
the person, the lady today, and I told
her that we were going to fight
it. Thank you.
M Miss Jones, I I'm meeting with uh
Director Campbell tomorrow and I I know
that Miss Bird had also followed up and
I thought that um we had gotten some
more information, but I will confirm
tomorrow and I'll I'll be in touch. I
took pictures that way you can see it. I
wasn't, you know, I'm not trying to hide
anything or whatever. I took pictures so
they can see what was what. You know, if
it was a lot of trash or something like
that, I can see it. But you're going to
charge me $200 for maybe picking up
something that came from the 100 block
or someplace else. You're going to
charge me
$225? No, that's not right. And it's not
just me. It's everybody. 19 people on
our blog. That's what the lady told me.
She said 19 people got citation. That
mean
from 100 block or whatever block it is
came blowing from wherever and we all
got a fine for
$225. Nuh-uh. That's not right.
Thank you.
I will I will um again I'm meeting with
Director Campbell tomorrow morning and I
will um uh talk with him about this. I
un I understood you brought these um
concerns previously. Yes. And
um I again I will make sure that someone
get and I appreciate that. Yes. And I
want to thank uh Councilwoman Diaz and
Councilman Lashard for responding to the
email that I had asked. We also asked
about a report for stop signs. We
haven't I guess that's coming to that is
um and so I Okay. Sorry. I sent your
email to the wrong Okay. An email
address that you don't use frequently.
Now I know and um we'll we'll get you
that information as well. Now thank you.
Um the other the thing I want to talk
about was that zone zoning ordinance
that got tabled. Is there an opportunity
that the proposal could be placed on
either the city website or a way that we
can get a copy of that to see what is
being proposed prior to you know it come
before council. Uh yeah, that was
actually introduced during the command
community community planning committee
uh during the last committee session.
Okay. That was the uh uh excuse me,
Langster Enterprise Elementary uh
reszoning and that that was tabled. Oh,
so it was for about the price. I did see
that. I didn't know that's what this was
in reference to. That was introduced
during the last community planning
meeting. Um this was supposed to be the
scheduled first reading, but that was uh
removed from the agenda. All right.
Thank you. Thank you, Miss Burton.
Jessica Lopez, completely off topic, but
um who's responsible for the removal of
no parking signs and handicap signs when
the people who asked for them no longer
reside there? That's traffic commission.
And if you send Mr. Harris a note. Um,
he can communicate with the staff at the
police bureau to send someone out to to
confirm that that person no longer lives
there and then Department of Public
Works goes out and removes the sign. Or
if it's like zoning, so say they put no
parking signs where there used to be a
garage and now said garage is a
house. Do they they should have removed
the sign, right? If said garage doesn't
have vehicles going in and out of it. I
live on a block that has street cleaning
every week and about four handicap spots
and no parking on one side. So, it's
like we need every space that we can get
on Manor Street. So, who reassesses when
the zoning is up? Cuz I can't walk up
and down Manor and figure out every spot
that should be fixed. Who does
that? Again, it's my understanding that
that is the purview of traffic
commission and I would send if you have
specific spots with an address like if
you can send a house number where there
is a handicap uh space in front um I
would also just say that um that we do
have a process of confirming that and so
that that's what traffic commission
does. So, um I mean just for future like
I appreciate the the response and the
information, but shouldn't there be like
um yearly 5yearly review when we're
literally being incarcerated for not
paying these parking tickets for places
that shouldn't
be? No, we do and we do have where where
you send in the information for Campbell
to look at and then the we basically
review it completely but we have to
initiate the process. You have to
initiate you would have to come also to
the meeting. So like that they you can
bring it forward to Yes. I I'm not sure
that you need to come to the meeting for
just they don't want me in any
meetings time thing because it's like at
3:00. No, but but what I'm what I'm
saying is shouldn't there be something
established where they do it without us
initiating it because we're busy working
for y'all tax money. Um that that
happens, but if someone moves before it
expires or like if somebody reszones a
property and they're like, "Oh, we want
to change this garage into a house.
Shouldn't a light go off and like ding
ding ding. Is there no parking sign?
Should we remove them?" That's what I'm
saying. Like when it comes to
accountability and transparency of the
people who are in place to actually do
the job, it's not on me to do the job. I
don't I live in one house. That that's
the thing. Like, yeah, I'm going to do
it for this one, but it's like, who's
going to do it for the other 12 houses
on the block and the other 50, 60, 90,
100 blocks in the city? People are
literally paying out their ass for
everything around here at this point. We
should have somebody who's like, you
know what, let's be smart and not piss
people off and just remove these signs.
Miss Lopez, if you want to uh send me
the the addresses, I can look into that
for you. Thank you so much. No problem.
Have a great rest of your day. Thank
you.
John Mer Strasburg, Pennsylvania. Um I
just want to leave you all with um one
last message tonight. Um I think it's
really pertinent. It's really important.
Um there are a whole lot of people in
this room in the city and this greater
community that I care for very deeply
and within the last month here um
talking from everybody from the city and
the county um I find that we again have
come back here to a city council meeting
united on a common front. Um now two
weeks ago we were united that we were
kind of shocked, disturbed and terrified
by the video how we saw it right that
was the common theme now we know we know
what happened after that I'm not here to
relitigate that but as I listen to all
of you on that side of the things and
the community here what I'm hearing is
that this community is afraid of the
Lancaster City Police Department that is
really not up for discussion and it
looks differently
The community behind me is addressing
their fear because they feel that there
is over policing going on. I sense a
fear from council and the mayor. That's
me just talking out loud because
policing at a national and state and
local level has just had its reckoning
over the last 5 years. George Floyd
wasn't in a vacuum. These are things
that we all have been facing and looking
at over the years. And it would be
disingenuous for any elected official to
act like there is not a policing issue
in America. Lchester has that same
problem and I see that there is a
collective fear or anxiety and it's for
different reasons. I understand that
it's for different reasons but we are
still united in that fear and within
that we need to negotiate on how to come
together. Lancaster city needs its own
truth and reconciliation.
We need a moment where we come together
like we have been and not just look at
this as a system that cannot be changed.
Think about it like this. The 13th
Amendment didn't just happen because
somebody said, "Oh, we're cool freeing
the slaves." Like, no. It was a fight. A
part tide didn't just end because Nelson
Mandela snapped his finger. That's not
how it happened. We can't accept the
status quo because the status quo is
unacceptable. And you guys know that
because you guys have done work over the
last 5 years, even though there's not
been a lot of credit thrown your way,
right? I I see that and there's credit
to be given to all of you. But right
now, that credit's not going to be
given. But I see the work you try to do.
I acknowledge that the working group was
a step in the direction. I acknowledge
all of you coming down to the protest in
2020 and 21. I acknowledge all that. I
know that you guys don't want a bad city
with bad police. I know that on my core,
but the actions don't the actions don't
reflect the words all the time. And
that's where you're
seeing the passion being directed
towards you all. So, I believe that you
guys want to do I believe that you think
that you want to do the right thing
here. And what I think is there is unity
in the disturbance of this issue. We're
still disturbed.
And I believe there's unity and that
there is a fear of the police force and
how they may react if city council does
something or how they may react with how
the mayor says something or interprets
something. There's a union. I get it. I
I I know you guys are humans, too. I
just want you to take that message and
let you know that I I see you. But we we
need to get past it. We need to come
together and have our own truth and
reconciliation and unite around that
fear and actually tangibly do something.
I thank you.
Hi, my name is Manda. I live on the
Where do I live? I live on Spruce
Street, the 500 block. Um, so I just
came up here to also address the police
brutality incident and um the public's
concern. Um, I can't get the voice out
of my head. um like call my mom, call my
mom. I can't believe that I had to hold
my breath while I was watching that
video the whole time, not knowing,
completely expecting that that video
would get worse like so much we've seen
in the news, in the media here in our
home, our hometown. I completely believe
that. I had to hold my breath because I
didn't trust what I was watching. I
didn't trust the Lancaster City police
with an innocent life in their hand and
a child at that. And why should that be
our reality when there are plenty of tax
dollars we put into police and the
deescalation and the training? The
presence of protection and public safety
is not lost upon us, but deranged beyond
measure, twisted into a tool that feels
more like a knife that's being sharpened
into our backs. These are our own
people, especially our black and black
and brown people in the community. We
need you to show up and show us that you
care. The excessive use of force is
unacceptable. the lack of security for
my friends, our family members, the
community here. I hold my breath again
cuz if the police aren't here for us,
then who are they who are they here for?
I think you've been really vague tonight
in dancing around your responses,
especially you, mayor. Um, in language
that doesn't even touch on the subjects.
You've given us an unclear image of what
the systems are in place. Um, but
please, we're not stupid. Help us under
understand, empower us. You've been
vague and uninterested, just
disingenuine interacting with your
community members and the needs, but
you're who we elected to take care of
us. And we've been clear. You've been
vague and we've been clear. So, what are
you going to do? So, we're asking again
for accountability for the officers
involved, public recognition of your
shortcomings, not just your excuses, and
to let you know we're afraid. Don't you
care?
help us. So, thank
you. Hi. Um, my name is Brandis Kevage.
I'm uh on the 700 block of Marietta
Avenue. Um, this is my first time
speaking up here, but um I moved here in
2022. Um, I moved here because I wanted
this to be a safe community for my son.
My husband is Haitian, so my son is
mixed. Um, I always watched that video
and all I could see um was my son on the
ground.
Um, and it made me
so. I expect that living here we are
safe, but it makes me wonder because my
son is not white and he is never going
to be seen as
that. Um, that could easily be him in 13
years. We're already facing a
constitutional crisis in our federal
government. People are already scared.
We don't need to be scared in our local
communities where we actually hold the
power.
So that's why I'm up here because I
can't remain
quiet. I hope in 13 years I don't have
to be standing here speaking about
this. Thank you.
Any additional public comment?
With that, we'll move on to the report
of the mayor, Mayor Sarra.
Okay. I'm going to talk about a few of
the things that have been addressed so
far this evening.
Um, council received a report um related
to our tree program and there was a
question about a $1 million America for
American Forest grant through the US
Forest Service to help bolster our
street tree program in our
neighborhoods. Um, as you know, a number
of our federal grants have been in
question and we've been working through
uh that as best as possible. I'm pleased
to let council know tonight that this
grant is moving forward uh and uh we
will be uh working in our neighborhoods
uh collectively to add more street
trees. Uh neighbors can submit their own
um have their own street tree planted
right now and there is more information
about the at this about this program at
the city of
lansterpa.gov/planting. Uh, I know that
Tina um, sorry, Director Campbell uh,
has already mentioned the good news
related to our bond rating as being
moved from an A3 stable to A3 positive.
Uh, as she mentioned, this not only
lowers our bond interest rates, but
affects other things that are always
considered related to future insurance
premiums and the like. Um, so I I just
want to also thank Director Campbell um
who has been in her position um just
over a year, 18 months, and has been
working diligently to continue to move
this the city forward uh with the home
rule study commission uh and the uh
increased uh financial reporting uh
especially as it relates to our capital
plan. All of those things are moving
forward. Uh you will be receiving your
first quarterly financial brief um in
April uh and re be receiving monthly
reports moving forward as well as those
quarterly financial reports. And I'm
underscoring this for a commissioner a
former commissioner uh Miss Bird um who
I know that that was something that was
important to you. Um and is important
just in general. Uh the other thing I
want to um let everybody know is that we
are continuing our quarterly testing of
POS in our water system and our recent
testing still has a running annual
average above the DP mandated limit for
PFOA POA in water source from the
Konosoga River. Lancaster County and
much of the state continues to be under
a drought watch which is a major
contributor to these higher results. And
so just you know remember running
averages if it is higher for a couple of
quarters that running average stays with
us until we have several quarters of
lower averages. The way that we get
lower averages is if it rains and
there's more water in the river. Um, I
wanted to make sure that for council's
awareness that uh each time we go above
the mandated running average, we must
send out a letter to all customers. And
I believe that those letters cost about
$25,000 each time we send a letter,
which we are required to do. And so we
will be spending another $25,000 in the
next few weeks uh to alert residents to
this fact. We continue to monitor this
issue, explore solutions um and
additional uh information about our PAS
and our testing results are posted on
the city of
linksterpa.gov. I also put in the caveat
always that drinking water represents
about 20% of your exposure to POS and
that drinking bottled water is uh not as
safe does not meet that have to meet the
same drinking water quality standards as
water that is produced by the city. And
so I just caveat that because buying
bottled water is not going to avoid
PAS. And that concludes my report
tonight.
Thank you, Mayor Sarra. Uh we'll move on
to the report of president of council.
Uh council council president did not
have a report for this evening. Uh
moving on to council comments. Um I'll
open it up for council to speak. If I
may, councelor Diaz, I just wanted to
address the gentleman in regards to the
immigration. I'm currently volunteering.
of my mean that I am bilingual and had
the opportunity to do intakes. If anyone
is interested, there's a parish, it's
called Parish Resource Center. It's at
2116 Lincoln Highway East and they if
you know anyone that need the resources
or the help that will be our attorneys
after the intake that will speak to
them. Thank you. That's what I have.
Thank you, councelor Diaz. Any
additional council
comments? Council colleagues. Thank you,
Council President. Um, in terms of
immigration, legal immigration as a
council member, there isn't much we can
do. Let's be
honest. So, what I can do, I can use my
voice, my platform, my vote. I can speak
out. And I have done that. You know, you
use newspaper, everybody needs to speak
out. And we can see that now many people
are silent. They don't speak out because
they are afraid.
And uh I want to let you know that I
support
um the call of the community. I support
the government's call for greater uh
transparency and I encourage the police
department to publicly release all past
use of
force and including the latest use of
force
reports, ensuring residents have access
to important public safety information.
Open communication is essential to
building trust and
accountability. I'm deeply concerned
about the incident and the response
provided in the press in the recent
press
conference. Our committee deserve full
transparency and accountability in such
matters. Our committee
deserve our committee deserves a
commitment to just and equitable
policing. Public safety is essential to
any community. It's
fundamental. But it's a collaboration
between local
government, police, and the
community. Clearly, that collaboration
is broken.
I'm in favor of any
measures any measures that can help
repair it up to and including a civil
review board.
I thought it's necessary to
engage in an open and transfer
discussion
between committee
members, city officials and
reinforcement to bring trust back to the
community. That's my comment for
tonight.
Thank you, Councelor
Le. Councelor Med. Uh thank you, Mr.
Vice President, and I just wanted to uh
react to the remarks of the gentleman
about the immigration. Uh there is a lot
of efforts going on at the state level
with uh different organizations here in
Lancaster that I am a part of and I
would love to connect with you and uh
talk about some of the activity we're
doing at the state
level. Thank you. Any additional council
comments? With that, I'll just end um
you know, one, I want to thank the
community for showing up tonight. Uh
similar to the last council meeting, um
you know, during the last council
meeting, I mentioned that you guys are
being heard and I want to continue to
echo that sentiment. Um I understand
that the press conference that was
recently given um didn't answer
everyone's questions. Um, one of the
things that I what I'm hearing from the
community is that uh there is broken
trust. I think one of the things that
we've learned from decades of of um you
know public safety efforts is that there
is a loss of trust there and as much as
we've done to rebuild it um to Miss
Lopez's point there is uh we must
maintain it and uh I want to make sure
that we continue to do so. Um there are
a couple initiatives that are underway.
One of the things that I'm committed to
doing is making sure that data continues
to be transparent and where it's not
transparent, where can we show more
historical data so that way we can see
some of the progress that we have made.
Um, I want you guys to hear from me. Uh,
and this is not picking sides. The the
one thing I do want to emphasize is that
no progress is made in separation. This
will take both the community, the police
department, city hall, and whatever new
administration walks into this build
building in 2026. It requires unity. It
can't be done through separation. Um, so
with that, I think there's opportunity
for more community engagement, whether
that's awareness on progress, whether
that's educational process or how can we
do better. And I think there's always
opportunities for improvement on both
sides. and you can be empathetic and
hold people accountable. And I will say
that goes for both sides. Our community,
our police department, we can hold each
other accountable. We can also be
empathetic in the process. Um, so I know
that doesn't answer anything. To Mr.
Miner's point, um, his stuff can't
happen with the snap of a finger. Uh,
culture eats strategy for breakfast and
it's important that we make sure that we
continue to build a culture in a
community where everyone feels safe. And
that will take time. Um, but continue
your advocacy. Continue to uh to speak
to your council members, your mayor, um,
your police officers. Building trust
starts with conversation. And I
appreciate you guys coming here to start
that. Thank
you. With no further council comments,
uh, I'll hear a motion to adjurnn.
Motion to adjurnn. Second. We have a
motion and a second. All those in favor?
I meeting ajourned.
Yeah, we don't have
Thanks for coming. Yeah, of course.